<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sea-man's obligations to gratitude and a good life a sermon preach'd in the parish-church of Deptford, in Kent, June 5, 1699, before the corporation of the Trinity-house at their annual meeting on Trinity-Monday / by George Stanhope ...</title>
            <author>Stanhope, George, 1660-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14516341</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14516341</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61276)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1071:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sea-man's obligations to gratitude and a good life a sermon preach'd in the parish-church of Deptford, in Kent, June 5, 1699, before the corporation of the Trinity-house at their annual meeting on Trinity-Monday / by George Stanhope ...</title>
                  <author>Stanhope, George, 1660-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Sare ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CVII, 23-24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sailors --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102495:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SEA-MAN'S Obligations to <hi>Gratitude</hi> and a <hi>Good Life.</hi> A SERMON Preach'd in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Deptford,</hi> in <hi>Kent, June</hi> 5. 1699. BEFORE THE Corporation of the <hi>Trinity-Houſe,</hi> At their Annual Meeting on <hi>Trinity-Monday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE STANHOPE,</hi> D.D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of that Honourable Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Sare,</hi> at <hi>Grays-Inn-Gate</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:102495:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102495:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm CVII. Verſe 23, 24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>They that go down to the Sea in Ships, and do buſineſs in great Waters:</p>
                  <p>Theſe Men ſee the Works of the Lord, and his Wonders in the Deep.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis Pſalm hath been interpreted by ſome,
<note place="margin">Auguſt. Enarr. in hunc Pſal.</note> as if it were one intire Allegory: The four Temporal Calamities mentioned here, denoting ſo many Spiritual Puniſhments, or Troubles upon the Mind. The Want and Wand'ring in the Wilderneſs,
<note place="margin">V. 3-8.</note> figuring Mens Errors and Ignorance of the right way to their Heavenly Country:
<note place="margin">V. 10-15.</note> The Captivity and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile, thoſe Difficulties in doing well, with which long offending does, as it were,
<note place="margin">V. 17-22.</note> clog and fetter har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'ned and habitual Sinners: the Sickneſs and want of Appetite, reſembling that general diſreliſh to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the things of God and Eternity, which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a carnal Life, and worldly Diſpoſition:
<note place="margin">V. 23-31.</note> And the Storms and Dangers at Sea made uſe of as a fit Emblem for the Trials and Toſſings of a boiſterous World, particularly for the Perſecutions of Good Men and the Truth: And ſince from all theſe things too God in his Mercy delivers Men upon their ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102495:3"/>Application to him, therefore <hi>David</hi> calls upon all thoſe for their Sacrifice of Thanks and Praiſe, who have at any time receiv'd ſuch valuable Bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Others there are,
<note place="margin">Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronym.</note> who have thought this a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of the Goſpel-Age; and, that by the Men in my Text particularly, who <hi>go down to the Sea in Ships, and do buſineſs in great Waters,</hi> are meant thoſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Bleſſed Saviour, who, from the Trade of Fiſhermen, were choſen to be Preachers of the Chriſtian Faith: That <hi>theſe Men ſaw the Works of the Lord, and his Wonders in the Deep,</hi> when God reveal'd to them the profound Myſteries of the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: Such as the Redemption of Mankind by a crucified Jeſus, the Trinity of Perſons in the Divine Eſſence, (which the Church, at this Seaſon more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, adores) and ſundry other Doctrines of our moſt Holy Religion, which no reach of humane Reaſoning can fathom, no Wit could have diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, had not God's own Spirit led Men into the Knowledge and Belief of them.</p>
            <p>But, waving theſe more diſtant Conſtructions, I ſhall keep cloſe to that moſt obvious and natural one, which the Pſalmiſt ſeems to have had firſt, if not only, in his view: And that is, from a Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſeveral Events of humane Life, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be proſperous or adverſe, whether private or publick, to awaken and ſtir Men up to a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of God and their Duty. For, that ſuch was his Deſign, ſeems abundantly manifeſt from that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102495:3"/>Concluſion of the Pſalm (V. 43.) <hi>Whoſo is wiſe will obſerve theſe things, and they ſhall underſtand the Loving Kindneſs of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, though ſuch a wiſe Obſervation be, no doubt, intended here, as, by convincing Men, that all theſe things are ordered by the Providence of God, might be a powerful Motive to the diſcharge of every part of their Duty; yet the Effect of it principally aimed at, is Thankſgiving; Publiſhing the <hi>Praiſes</hi> of that <hi>God for his Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>declaring the Wonders that he doth for the Children of Men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 8 V. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> V. 2 V. 3</note> This is the Exhortation ſo often repeated, and ſo earneſtly inculcated here, and urged from a Recollection of the many Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and ſore Diſtreſſes, out of which the Great Governor of the World, who diſpoſes our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of every kind, reſcues them, who in Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty flee to Him for Refuge. This Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he calls upon all People to pay; becauſe the Inſtances of the Divine Goodneſs are ſo many, ſo conſpicuous, that it muſt argue great Inadvertency, not to ſee, and reflect upon them, when they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to Others: But this he requires in a peculiar manner from Them, who have had Experience of that Goodneſs themſelves. For, if the eminent Proofs of ſuch a Providence ought, and will natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally not fail, to move us, when we are meer Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by, and Spectators only; it muſt certainly betray a very wretched degree of Stupidity, and a horrible Unworthineſs, for Men to continue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102495:4"/>and inſenſible, who have perſonally felt and taſted that the Lord is gracious: For ſuch to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain no becoming Impreſſions, no religious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances, of either thoſe amazing Dangers, or thoſe ſeaſonable and wonderful Preſervations, which have been brought home to them, and made their own Caſe.</p>
            <p>Again, if barren Deſarts, and dark Priſons; if Beds of Languiſhing and Storms at Sea, do, by an almoſt irreſiſtible Neceſſity, drive the profaneſt and moſt profligate Wretches to their Prayers: and, if,
<note place="margin">V. 5.13, 19, 28.</note> when ſuch as theſe <hi>cry unto the Lord in their trouble, he</hi> do not diſdain to hear, and <hi>deliver them out of their diſtreſs;</hi> What can excuſe thoſe Vagabonds and Captives, thoſe once ſick, and juſt ſinking Men, if they ſhall not be as liberal and as loud in their Praiſes afterwards, as formerly they were in their Calls and Complaints; if they ſhall neglect to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie before all the World, that they look upon God as their Saviour and mighty. Deliverer, and own their preſent Safety and Succeſſes to be entirely the Work of a Wiſe, and Kind, and Omnipotent Providence?</p>
            <p>This is evidently the Sum of the Prophet's Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Pſalm before us: The Force whereof might without great difficulty be illuſtrated from any of the Caſes ſpecified in it; but from never a one of them, I think, to better advantage, than that to which my Text, and the Quality of this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102495:4"/>Audience and Solemnity, now determine me. For if there be any ſort of People, who have not only obſerved, but perpetually converſed with, invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible demonſtrations of a God and Providence; if any, whoſe Obligations to Religion and Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are more ſenſible, more indiſpenſable, than thoſe of Common Men, where may we reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly expect to find theſe, rather than among them; <hi>who go down to the Sea in Ships and do buſineſs in great Waters,</hi> who in ſo ſignal a manner <hi>ſee the VVorks of the Lord, and his VVonders in the Deep?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Perſons ſpoken of in my Text, are not they who make Vorages or Pleaſure or Convenience, but ſuch as make the Sea their Occupation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant way of living. And to theſe I ſhall direct my Diſcourſe at preſent, by treating of the Words, and the thing intended by them, under the Two fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>First,</hi> I ſhall endeavour, I will not ſay, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, (for who can fairly be ſupposd ignorant of ſo obvious and evident a Truth?) but rather to put ſuch in remembrance, that the Dangers and Deliverances peculiar to this courſe of Life, are the Effects of a Divine Providence. And then, <hi>Secondly,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. I ſhall ſhew what Influence this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought to have upon all, who have had the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102495:5"/>Experience of ſuch a watchful and powerful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Firſt, I ſay, the Dangers and Deliverances proper to a Sea-faring Life are eminently the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a Divine Providence. The ſame Reaſon, which convinces every thinking Man, that this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial World, and each part of it, muſt needs have been framed by ſome Eternal and Infinite Being, will, when purſued through its juſt Conſequences, teach us to conclude alſo, that theſe things now can no more govern and preſerve themſelves, than they could originally make themſelves. The wond'rous Order and regular Proceſs, obſervable in Natural Cauſes and Effects, do indeed illuſtrate the Wiſdom and Management; but they do by no means wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Belief, or take away the Neceſſity, of a Higher and Super-intending Power. For, that theſe lower Agents do in moſt Caſes operate alike, proves them to be confined to Rule and Method; but, that they do not always produce the ſame Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, is no leſs an Evidence, that they are under the direction of a Supreme Cauſe, which checks, and limits, and over-rules their Influences, as he ſees fit. Thus both the regular and the excepted Caſes conſpire to prove the Being and Providence of God. Since there is in all the Works of Nature ſo much Conſtancy, as argues the World to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by an intelligent Being; and yet ſo much
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102495:5"/>variety in Events, and ſo ſurprizing Changes too, as evidence that Being to be an Agent free in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations, and abſolute in his Dominion; that none of the moſt uniform Productions are fixed by a fatal Neceſſity; none of the moſt efficacious Means ſo ſure of ſucceeding, as never to be put by their ordinary Courſe; none, in a word, exempted from the Countermand of his Diſpoſal.</p>
            <p>We ſhall do well then to conceive of Almighty God, as of a wiſe and watchful Pilot, always at the Helm, and ſteering his own World, taking the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of natural Inſtruments, and letting this great Veſſel drive before them, ſo long as theſe, like proſperous Gales and favourable Tides, make way for his good Purpoſes: But when they bear down hard, and grow too violent, then interpoſing his Skill and Strength, ſhifting the Courſe, or check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Current, or by ſome other Arts to us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, bringing the moſt furious, the moſt irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible Efforts of Created Nature in Subjection to the Counſel of his own Will.</p>
            <p>And if this be, as certainly it is, the State of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and the World in general, then, where theſe Interpoſitions are moſt frequent and viſible; where ſuch Agents and Cauſes, as ſeem moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governable, do yet ſubmit to ſuch Reſtraints, and become flexible and uſeful; where Humane Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which can only proceed upon regular and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Operations, are moſt impotent, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102495:6"/>at a loſs; there we cannot, with any fair and probable Reaſoning, but aſcribe ſuch Events, as are contrary to, or above the reach of, Matter and Motion, to the marvelous Addreſs and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Efficacy of that wiſe and powerful Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.19.</note> who (as this Pſalmiſt ſays elſewhere) <hi>ſitteth in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and ruleth over all from the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this Account, we may very well ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, it is, that the Scripture does, upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, take ſuch particular Care to aſſert and incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate that Government which God exerciſes over the Winds and the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eas: For theſe are parts of Nature, fierce and impetuous above the reſt, various and uncertain in their Motions; the moſt unaccountable, the moſt unmanageable, of all the Creatures in this lower World; and, by conſequence, the moſt pregnant Teſtimonies of an over-ruling Providence, in all thoſe aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing and mighty Alterations, which we ſo frequently perceive in them. Hence God is ſaid to
<note n="a" place="margin">Jer. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>ſet bounds to the</hi> Sea,
<note n="b" place="margin">Hag. 2.7.</note> to <hi>ſhake it,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Job 38.8.</note> to <hi>ſhut it up with doors;</hi> to
<note n="d" place="margin">Iſai. 50.2</note> 
               <hi>dry it up,</hi> to
<note n="e" place="margin">Nah. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>rebuke it,</hi> to ſtill
<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 89.8.65.7.</note> 
               <hi>its roarings,</hi> and <hi>ſilence the noiſe of its waves when they rebel;</hi> and that,
<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 93.5.</note> 
               <hi>though its waters be mad, and rage horribly, yet ſtill the Lord who dwelleth on high is mightier.</hi> So again, the Winds are very empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically ſtiled the
<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 148.8.</note> Winds of God, and the
<note n="i" place="margin">Job 37.9.10.</note> Breath of God; with theſe he is ſaid <hi>to blow,</hi> and the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſwell;</hi> Theſe
<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>35.7.</note> he <hi>brings out of his Treaſures;</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102495:6"/>with theſe he
<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 29. and 148.</note> 
               <hi>rends the Mountains, ſcatters his Cold and Froſt,
<note n="m" place="margin">Job 37.10.</note> ſtraitens the Waters, and hardens them like ſolid Metal.</hi> And farther yet, for theſe he is ſaid to make
<note n="n" place="margin">Job 28.25</note> Weights and Meaſures, to
<note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 27.8.</note> ſtay their rougheſt and moſt tumultuous Inſults, quell all their boiſterous Rage, and with a <hi>Peace be ſtill,</hi> huſh their Noiſe and Confuſion into a profound Calm. And, to go no farther than this Paſſage now before us; the <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Wonders</hi> here aſcrib'd to God, are expreſſed (V. 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) by the <hi>Storm ariſing at his Word,</hi> the Waves of the Sea rolling and foaming, toſſing Men up to Heaven, and ſinking them down again to Hell; driving them to their Wits end, and damping the very ſtouteſt of them all; and yet, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then, when neither Courage nor Conduct, neither Hearts nor Hands are of any longer Service, God continues the ſame ſtill: He is not deaf to Men's Prayers; nor are theſe rudeſt and moſt rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all Elements deaf to his Reproofs, but even the Storms fulfill his Word, and blow but by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: He finds no difficulty in quieting the Tempeſt, and ſmoothing the Face of the Deep; but raiſes and inſtantly fixes the hearts melted down with Anguiſh and Deſpair juſt before, and makes them glad by ſetting them <hi>at reſt,
<note place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> and bringing them to the Haven, where they would be.</hi> This gets him an indiſputable Title to ſuch Men's Praiſes; The ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring them in an Extremity, when humane helps could avail nothing, when even Hope it ſelf was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102495:7"/>loſt, when any Power leſs than divine muſt have been defeated in the Attempt to deliver them.</p>
            <p>But in all Caſes of this Nature, it is not enough to be ſatisfied that God is the Doer and Diſpoſer of them, unleſs we be likewiſe careful to obſerve with what deſign he does them, and what thoſe Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are, which he would have ſerved, by the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips we ſuſtain, the dangers we are threat'ned with, and the ſurprizing Reſcues from, or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes after them.</p>
            <p>Now, though we are not allow'd to judge of the Proportion of any Man's Virtue or Guilt, or God's Love or Hatred toward him, by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Good or Evil, which befals him in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life: Yet thus much in the general is true, that all Afflictions are, and ought to be received, as Chaſtiſements of Sin, and all Deliverances ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged as Marks of God's Favour and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Bleſſings, 'tis true, may by our own Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>management be converted into Curſes and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Ruine: And Sufferings, by a prudent Virtue, may be exalted into the moſt valuable Mercies. The former may be plentifully impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Wicked, and the latter made the Portion of the Juſt: But ſtill this hinders not, why, ſpeaking of theſe Diſpenſations at large, the Pſalmiſt here, and we by his Example, may not attribute Mens Calamities to their Faults which had provoked God; and their better Succeſſes to ſome behaviour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102495:7"/>well-pleaſing in his ſight.
<note place="margin">V. 9.10.</note> Thus we find <hi>Mens being bound in Affliction and Iron,</hi> charged <hi>upon their rebelling againſt the Words of God,</hi> and <hi>contemning the Counſel of the moſt High.</hi> And <hi>Fools</hi> are ſaid, <hi>becauſe of their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion to be plagued with Sickneſs,
<note place="margin">V. 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> to abhor all manner of Meat, and to draw nigh to the Gates of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is confeſt, that no ſuch Cauſe is poſitively aſſigned here; but ſure there is nothing particular in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the thing, which ſhould forbid us applying it to Storms and Shipwrecks, as well as to Impriſonment and Bodily Diſeaſes. But in the Mercies mentioned throughout this Pſalm, there is no Place for probable Conjectures; for in every one of theſe, expreſs No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice is taken of its being a Reward to them, who fled to God for Succour, and took Sanctuary in Him, when other Helps and Comforts had forſaken them. And hence the Duty of Praiſe is urged as a neceſſary Inſtance of Gratitude, for ſo ready an Acceptance, ſo ſucceſsful a Return, of ſuch Prayers: For that you ſee is the conſtant burthen of this Holy Song; <hi>When they cried unto the Lord in their Trouble,
<note place="margin">V. 8.13.15, 19, 21, 28, 31.</note> and he delivered them out of their Diſtreſs: O that Men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his Goodneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Wonders that he doth for the Children of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Without entring then into any Niceties concerning this Matter, or ſhewing how far temporal Good and Evil are from diſtinguiſhing Characters of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Affection and Diſpleaſure, though at the ſame time the One be moſt truly the Effect of God's
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102495:8"/>Goodneſs, and the Other of Man's Sin; I ſhall take it for granted, that all who conſider the different Events of humane Life to be the Work of God, do likewiſe allow them to be wrought with ſome wiſe Deſign; and that each ſort requires ſome Uſe and Improvement to be made of it, in proportion to its Nature and Quality: And thus much is ſufficient to ground my other general Head upon, wherein I propoſed to ſhew,</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> What Influence the Conſideration of Mens Dangers and Deliverances being all from God, ought to have upon Them, whoſe own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath convinced them of ſuch a watchful and powerful Providence; ſuch, as is over thoſe particularly, <hi>who by going down to the Sea in Ships, and following their buſineſs in great Waters, have ſeen the Works of the Lord, and his Wonders in the Deep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only Fruit inſiſted on here is Thankfulneſs; nor had the Prophet occaſion to demand more; for this alone, when rightly grounded, and diligently cultivated, is ſo noble a Product, and of ſo large Extent, that, as to be reproached with Unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs is a Character of univerſal Infamy; ſo to be truly thankful for the Mercies of God, is, in the juſt Latitude of the Word, but another Name for a Good Man, and a Good Chriſtian. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. No Man doubts, but this implies never dying Remembrances, and very warm and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate Reſentments of the Benefits we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102495:8"/>And, in regard that out of ſuch abundance of the Heart the Mouth will naturally ſpeak, from hence will follow,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Free and publick Declarations of God's Love and Mercy upon all fit Occaſions. Nor yet only ſo, but</p>
            <p n="3">3. A conſtant Care not to diſpleaſe or affront One, who hath been ſo bountiful to, and tender of Us. For to profeſs grateful Reſentments, without atteſting to them by reſpectful Behaviour, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Inſincerity; and to proclaim our Obligations to a Perſon, whom we diſoblige in return, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach our ſelves with the greateſt Baſeneſs, and to publiſh our Hypocriſy to all the World. Nay,</p>
            <p n="4">4. True Gratitude will think it ſelf concerned to vindicate the Honour, and promote the Advantage, of its Benefactor. And That which is ſo toward God, will ſtudy to advance his Glory; and by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Perſwaſion, or ſuch other Methods, as the Perſon's Circumſtances qualify him for, will labour to gain over others to a reverent and juſt Opinion of Him, and of that Religion, which he is pleaſed in condeſcenſion to call his Cauſe and Intereſt, and the doing him Service.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A Man truly Thankful for Succours received heretofore, will, with great Contentedneſs and a chearful Faith, depend upon God in any Diſtreſſes for the time to come. Even our Friends upon Earth take it ill to be diſtruſted, who yet have little in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102495:9"/>their Power, and but ſeldom very much in their Will. But what can be a greater Indignity, than to ſuſpect the Care, or be uneaſy under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, of that Friend above, who cannot deceive, who will not forſake us; eſpecially after many ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and ſurpriſing Experiments, both of his Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and his Ability, to do us good?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, They who are Thankful for paſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, will be compaſſionate to others in the like Danger and Diſtreſs. The Remembrance of their own Caſe will diſpoſe them to this Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as Men; and, as Chriſtians, they will need no other Incitement, than this ſingle Reflection, That they who relieve the leaſt of their Lord's Members, do it to Himſelf. So that This is in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a paying back the Kindneſs; a Thing which true Gratitude eagerly takes all Opportunities of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And, though the Return be not made, either in Kind, or in Quantity, yet it is ſuch as poor Mortals are capable of; ſuch as argues their Wiſhes and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to do more; and ſuch as He, whoſe Debtors they are, is content to accept for good Payment.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all ſo genuine, ſo neceſſary Evidences of Thankfulneſs; and the Reaſonableneſs of them is ſo obvious, that I ſhall not hold my ſelf obliged to enlarge upon our Engagements to them. No Benefactor among Men looks upon himſelf well treated upon other Terms; and he, who declines any of theſe upon proper Occaſions, all his diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102495:9"/>Profeſſions ought, and will be ſure with Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to go for nothing. And therefore all I ſhall do more, is only to apply my ſelf to this Aſſembly, with regard to each of the foregoing Particulars, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then: For the begetting in you becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſentments for the Mercies of God in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, I ſhall not, I need not, attempt any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Deſcription of the infinite Hazards, or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Providences, peculiar to that manner of Life, in which the Education and Affairs of ſo many now before me have engaged them: The Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and the Works of Wiſdom, which converſing with remote Countries hath made you Eye-witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of; nor the Difficulties and ſundry kinds of Death, which diſtant Climates, and eſpecially your Paſſage to and from them, have ſo often expoſed you to. You know very well, that the Terrours of a Storm, or a Wreck, are but feebly repreſented by Words; and that Experience leaves behind it more lively and laſting Images of this kind, than all the laboured Rhetorick in the World. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients ſeem to have ſo juſt a Notion of this Matter, as to make it almoſt a Proverb,
<note place="margin">O fortuna te neſcis quantum periculi praeterie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, qui nunquan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> es ingreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Mare.</note> That <hi>He who hath never been at Sea, can ſcarcely know what it is to be in Danger.</hi> And then ſurely They who have known, and felt, and lived conſtantly in, and often eſcaped from This; This, in compariſon whereof nothing it ſeems was eſteemed dreadful enough to deſerve the Name
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102495:10"/>of Danger, theſe Men cannot eaſily be ſuppoſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to forget it.</p>
            <p>And yet it muſt be confeſs'd, with regard to Your Caſe, that thoſe Ancients were but little, and the Age of <hi>David</hi> not at all, acquainted with the moſt formidable part of that, which Your good God hath carried You through. The only Perils They had in view, were ſuch as grow from Winds, and Waves, and warring Elements: Nor were Men then aware of any other End of <hi>going down to the Sea in Ships,</hi> but that of <hi>doing</hi> the <hi>Buſineſs</hi> of Traffick there. And, What is the Fatigue, What the Hazard of This, when ſet againſt the very diſtant Uſes which later Times have found for theſe <hi>Great Waters,</hi> and the fatal Improvement ſince made to the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Dangers? For, as if even the moſt mercileſs Parts of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation had been too ſparing and tender of our Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Men induſtrious in the Art of Killing, have brought the Two moſt cruel, the Two moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lements in the World, to conſpire toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and mutually to aſſiſt in the more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Deſtruction of Mankind. They have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived to burn one another in the Water, to drown their Enemies in liquid Fire, to turn their Veſſels into floating Batteries, and make the Ocean itſelf a Field of Blood. It is in this moſt frightful Form, that ſeveral of You have often met Death: And ſhall I ſuppoſe it poſſible, that ſuch complicated Horrours can ever ſlip out of your Minds? That
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102495:10"/>you ſhould not frequently and ſeriouſly recollect, who made ſo gracious a Diſtinction in the Day of Battle, when Thouſands fell beſide you, and Ten thouſand at your Right-hand, and yet the fatal Ball came not nigh you? No, no. You ſtand here this Day ſo many living Monuments of Mercy, ſo many undeniable Demonſtrations of a wonderful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and you muſt not, you cannot forget God, while you continue to remember your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If then this be, as I ought to preſume it is, the inward Senſe of your Souls, your Obligations to the <hi>Second</hi> Thing are very apparent, That of making your Thanks ſolemn and publick. This the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet requires (Ver. 32.) that ſuch as have eſcaped the Perils of the Sea, <hi>would exalt God in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the People, and praiſe him in the Seat of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> His meaning is, That theſe open Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments are a Tribute due for Deliverances ſo eminent; becauſe they ſet forth the Glory of God, they put others upon obſerving, how Wiſe, and Powerful, and Good he is, and encourage all that ſee and hear them, to ſerve and depend upon One ſo Able, ſo Ready, to help them that ſeek him. But there is yet another Reaſon, which ſhould move Them to it, whoſe Lives have been expoſed upon the publick Account: For it is no ſmall Mercy, that God hath made Such, Inſtruments of a general Good to their Country. You therefore are bound, above all Men, to <hi>praiſe God in the Congregation of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102495:11"/>People,</hi> becauſe the whole Congregation will not fail to praiſe God, not only with you, but for you. If Trade flouriſh, and Wealth increaſe, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Your Induſtry and Courage tranſplant the Product of diſtant Countries hither, and make all their Conveniencies ours. If this Iſland enjoy the Benefits of its happy Situation, it is becauſe that Sea, which God hath made our Rampart and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment, hath been ſtoutly defended by our Navies: Without theſe, the Nation muſt be ſo far from rich and proſperous, that it could not ſo much as be ſafe. And that which renders us ſo uſeful to our Friends, ſo formidable to our Enemies, and ſo ſecure from Foreign Invaſions, is not ſo much our Numbers, or our Home-growth, or our Wall of Waters; as the Advantages of our Commerce A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and the invincible Valour of our Fleets at Home. This we juſtly eſteem our proper Strength, and to it, under God, aſcribe our Glory and Protection: And therefore They who do gallantly, and are ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful upon theſe Occaſions, are much to blame, if They do not publiſh the Praiſes of God, becauſe they are ſure to meet with ſo many diſpoſed to join in thoſe Praiſes with them. For ſuch we pray and faſt when in Action and Danger; and, in ſo doing, we pray and faſt for our ſelves. And when ſuch return with Victory or Peace, they engage us to come into their Thanks, not only as Chriſtians, but as Parties; not out of Fellow-feeling, but Self-love.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102495:11"/>Their Intereſt and ours is one and the ſame; we all find a vaſt account in their Safety; and, in their Conqueſts and Deliverances, do in effect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate our own.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They who have proceeded thus far, ought to be put in mind, that the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Part of Thankfulneſs is ſtill behind; that, I mean, which conſiſts in the Man's Actions and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour. For, as in ſuch Benefactors among Men, whoſe Condition ſets them ſo much above us, that they do not need, or we cannot repay what we have received from them, in kind, the only way left us to teſtifie our Gratitude, is by reſpecting, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and doing them Honour and Service; ſo, and much more is it, in the Benefits we receive from the Great and moſt High God. We are therefore taught in our excellent Liturgy to pray for ſuch a due ſenſe of his Mercies, as may make us <hi>unfeignedly thankful,</hi>
               <note place="margin">General Thanſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> and prove that <hi>we are ſo, by ſhewing forth his Praiſe, not only with our Lips, but in our Lives.</hi> Now, if the beſtowing Life and Being at firſt do veſt in him a Title to our Obedience, then, ſo oft as this Gift is repeated, ſo much the more that Claim is ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The very Deſign, in truth, of all his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings is to invite, and encourage, and (by Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the moſt forcible of any to an ingenuous Temper) even to conſtrain us to Virtue and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; to make us in love with ſo kind a Maſter, and chearful in doing our utmoſt for Him, who hath done
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102495:12"/>ſo much for Us. And which way can We evade this Obligation, eſpecially when the moſt we can do for him is ſo much leſs than his due, and the leaſt he hath done for us ſo much more than our deſert? After a long Recital of the many Miracles in behalf of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> God is ſaid to have wrought them all for this very purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.14.</note> 
               <hi>that they might keep his Statutes, and obſerve his Laws.</hi> And in another Place, this is mention'd as the dreadfulleſt aggravation of that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples wickedneſs, that <hi>they forgot, and rebelled againſt God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.</note> who had done ſo great things for them.</hi> But what need I urge Chriſtian-Inſtances and Arguments, when nothing can be plainer from the very Nature of Gratitude, than that each Perſon ought to make his diligence in pleaſing God hold proportion with the marks of his having been the peculiar Care of his Providence, and be as ſignally religious, as he hath been ſignally bleſſed?</p>
            <p>If then, as was before obſerved, the Affairs of ſo many here preſent have been ſo full of hazard, and their Deliverances ſo full of wonder, it will lye upon their Conſciences very ſeriouſly to examine, what ſort of requital they have made for theſe Mercies. Moſt certain it is, God does not ſave Men from the Sea, and the Sword, that when they come aſhore <hi>they may give themſelves up to the</hi> Devil's <hi>Service,</hi> and <hi>walk before him without fear in Unholineſs and Unrighteouſneſs all the days of their life.</hi> He expects to have his Name called upon after another manner, than in Oaths,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102495:12"/>and Curſes, and blaſphemous Terms of Defiance and Contempt. He will account ſeverely with thoſe Wretches, who dare his Vengeance, and cry aloud to him to rot thoſe Bodies, and to damn thoſe Souls, which he with ſo Fatherly a Tenderneſs hath reſcued from Deſtruction. My Deſign herein is not to upbraid, or accuſe, but ſeaſonably to warn, the Men of this Profeſſion, that they wo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld conſider in time, how large an Article in their laſt great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the Good Providence of God over them in their Dangers and Neceſſities will one day make; and that it were better, infinitely better for them, to have fallen by the Enemies hand, or to have been drown'd in the depth of the Sea, than to have ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both to no other Effect, than that moſt ſad one of enflaming their Reckoning, and heating their Furnace ſeven times hotter, by their horrible Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Abuſe of ſuch marvelous Loving Kindneſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But I ſaid before, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> that a true Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Thankfulneſs will not allow Men to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with their own private Virtue, but will render them zealous Promoters of God's Glory, by winning over others to his Service. The Methods and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for effecting this differ greatly, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Mens different Stations and Capacities in the World. But I eſteem my ſelf happy in addreſſing this day to ſeveral worthy Perſons, whoſe Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Poſts of Command may be exceeding uſeful in this Particular: Perſons, whoſe good Example
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102495:13"/>may inſpire, and whoſe Diſcipline may enforce, the Exerciſe of Religion; At leaſt theſe could not fail to diſcountenance Vice, and give a check to the Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of open Immorality and Profaneneſs. You are, my Brethren, Men of Honour; and that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter will not endure, that your Prince, or your Friend ſhould be ill treated in your Preſence: Can it then conſiſt with this Character patiently to ſee and hear the King of kings, and your beſt Friend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, affronted and reviled? Your Honourable So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety derives its Name from the holy and ever-bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity; and will not that Title reproach eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Member of this Body, who, without puniſhment or due rebuke, ſhall ſuffer the Majeſty of the <hi>Father</hi> to be deſpiſed, the Blood and Wounds of the <hi>Son</hi> to be invoked in ſport and deriſion, and contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſpite to be done to the <hi>Spirit of Grace?</hi> The moſt glorious Improvement of Navigation would be to ſpread Chriſtianity wider, and enlighten the ſtill dark Corners of the Earth with ſaving Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and the readieſt way of compaſſing this noble end would be, by making the Light of thoſe who already profeſs the Goſpel, ſo to ſhine in barbarous Countries, that our good Works might recommend, and demonſtrate the Excellence of our Faith.</p>
            <p>Live then, my Brethren, as becomes them whom the Lord hath redeem'd, and deliver'd from Perils various, and Deaths oft: Live ſo, that Strangers
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102495:13"/>who are not yet acquainted with the Doctrine of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> may read it plainly in your Converſations: Live ſo, that, having firſt reform'd your ſelves, you may, with boldneſs and a good grace, reprove, and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout reforming others. And let thoſe under your Conduct ſee, that you are in very good earneſt; and that you think the Honour of your Poſt concerned for no ſort of Order and Diſcipline more, than for that, which hath reſpect to Virtue, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. It hath been ſaid formerly,
<note place="margin">Qui neſcit orare, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendat mare.</note> that <hi>he who would learn to be devout ſhould go to Sea:</hi> And, I dare ſay, You would be loath to have ſuch an Infamy fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Your days, as that of reverſing the Obſervation, and having the Sea thought the ready Courſe for transforming Men into Infidels and Brutes. As therefore you have done in the Cauſe of your King and Country, ſo behave your ſelves valiantly in the Cauſe of your God. Vice, it is true, hath gathered ſtrength, and with an unuſual confidence ſeems to bid all good Men Battle. But Vice is never ſo tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, that Reſolution may not bring it under. Let but that Gallantry appear in this Point, ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Fleets of <hi>England</hi> in others, that of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down upon the Enemy again and again, and the day is certainly your own. Sin carries Shame and Cowardice in its very Nature, and cannot rally of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: And be aſſur'd, this is a Conqueſt, which, when once throughly obtain'd, would bring more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to your ſelves, and more true Honour to your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102495:14"/>Memories, than thoſe which, at the Expence of ſo much Blood and Toil, tranſmit the Names of this Fraternity down to ſucceeding Generations. Nor are you ever more properly in your Poſt, than when encount'ring this Adverſary; for the Sins of a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and eſpecially of that part whoſe Duty it is to fight for the reſt, are always the moſt deſtructive Enemy that can make War upon any Nation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When your Zeal for God and the Publick hath thus exerted it ſelf, then are you rightly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the <hi>Fifth</hi> Branch of Thankfulneſs, that of Truſt in God, amidſt any Dangers, which ſhall hereafter threaten or attack you. And, however diſmal theſe may appear, yet your former Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of that Power and Goodneſs, which hath ſo ſignalized it ſelf on your behalf, will be of mighty uſe towards drawing down upon them with Brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For God is never weary of doing good; but his paſt Bleſſings are ſo many Pledges of more and better, provided we be careful not to ſtop the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; nor by our Unworthineſs, and Abuſe of thoſe already received, put a Bar to his Intentions of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Favour toward us. If then your own lawful Occaſions, or your Country's Defence, ſhall call you out again to the like hazardous Attempts, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber under the ſhadow of whoſe VVings you were ſafe heretofore, and that he is the <hi>the ſame, yeſterday, and to day,
<note place="margin">Heb 13 8. Iſai 63.1. Pſal. 37.</note> and forever, even the Lord, rich in Mercy, and mighty to ſave. He will not forſake his that be godly, nor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102495:14"/>ſhall they be confounded in the perilous Time:</hi> So ſays this Pſalmiſt, and ſo infinite Paſſages of Holy Scripture beſides. Places, which deſerve the rather to be conſidered, becauſe, when Art and Nature have done their utmoſt, ſtill nothing goes ſo far toward inſpiring Men with true Courage, and undaunted Preſence of Mind, as an Innocent Life, and a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt Faith. Theſe only can furniſh Men with that threefold impenetrable Defence, of which no Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors can diſarm them, A Good Cauſe, A Good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and a Good God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. There is yet a <hi>Sixth</hi> Particular behind; and that is, Readineſs to ſuccour all them, whom the like Dangers and Diſaſters have reduced to want your Relief. For, how are you thankful, if the eſcaping theſe do not open your Bowels to ſuch of your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who actually ſuffer what you had alſo felt, if God in Mercy had not put a difference between You and Them? I have already hinted, that both Common Humanity and Chriſtian Charity jointly plead in this Cauſe: And plead they do, with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which, ſince too ſtrong to be anſwer'd, ſhould be too powerful to be deny'd. And, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, where no Man's Abilities extend to the ſupply of all that want, great Diſcretion is requiſite in the Choice of fit Objects for our Charity; I ſhould not be juſt to the occaſion of our preſent Meeting, did I forbear to ſay, that no Poverty, ſuſtained upon Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts purely ſecular, no Liberality, which propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102495:15"/>to it ſelf Civil Advantages only, hath a better Title to our Gifts, than that, wherein diſabled Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and their neceſſitous Families are concern'd. Their Claim in truth is ſuch, that I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Relief ſhould not be rather call'd a Debt, than a Gift. The Wealth of this Nation is in ſo great part imported by thoſe in the Merchants Service, and the quiet Poſſeſſion of the whole ſo manifeſtly ſecured by thoſe in his Majeſty's; that what we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow in this way, is but ſome ſmall proportion of that which the Receivers have either help'd to get us, or have hind'red the Enemies taking away from us. And are we Men, if we can ſuffer ſo vile a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, as the ſeeing Thoſe, whoſe Induſtry hath filled our Stores, whoſe Valour hath fought our Battles, at the Expence of whoſe Sweat and Blood it is that our Portion is grown fat and plenteous: If we can bear, I ſay, to ſee Theſe, or their Relicts periſh, when Wounds, and loſs of Limbs, when Sickneſs, or Age, or an untimely Death, have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'red Them or Theirs incapable any longer, not only of ſerving the Publick, but of ſupporting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? The Rule of Equity, the Senſe of our own Benefit, and the Common Intereſt, which depends ſo much upon giving all due Encouragement (I had almoſt ſaid in giving all Honour and Reſpect) even to the meaneſt Subjects, who ſuffer in their Countries Cauſe, require not only Compaſſion, but Generoſity, from all in Circumſtances to extend it.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102495:15"/>But moſt of all from You, whom God hath ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd, and ſo bleſs'd, as to make that very Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment the Foundation of Your better Fortunes, by which ſo many of your Brethren have ruin'd theirs.</p>
            <p>And,
<note place="margin">Act for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtring, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging of Seamen.</note> if ſuch Reaſons needed to be ſeconded by Examples, We in this juncture, God be bleſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with them. The Great Council of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have wiſely found their Honour and Safety con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to make a laſting Proviſion for this purpoſe. And the Glorious Preſerver of our Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, accounts it no Indignity to a Royal Palace,
<note place="margin">Greenwich <hi>Hoſpital.</hi>
               </note> to be converted into a comfortable Retreat for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay'd, and a fruitful Seminary for growing, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and Mariners. He, who hath been ſo liberal of his own Blood for our Defence, could not but bear a juſt and very tender regard to Them who ſhed Theirs in it. And You, who have ſo well imitated the Courage of your Prince, will, I doubt not, be as powerfully provoked to Charity, by the ſame Argument and Example. The weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Truſt already repoſed in your hands, and the careful and wiſe Management of it, do not only prove the Diſpoſition of faithful Stewards, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that of bountiful Benefactors.</p>
            <p>Omitting therefore any farther Enlargement, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Subject, which ſpeaks ſo movingly for it ſelf, I conclude all with hearty Prayers to God, That
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102495:16"/>He, who hath ſhewed you the Works and Wonders of his Goodneſs ſo plenteouſly, would give you Grace to be unfeignedly thankful; That he would make you ſucceſsful Inſtruments of promoting his Glory, and the Publick Good, by your Examples, by your Authority, by reforming the Vicious, and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Debauchery and Profaneneſs in all under your Command; by doing valiantly for your Country, and by ſhewing Mercy to your Brethren in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: In one Word, that God would grant us a Succeſſion of Good and Gallant Men, to maintain the Safety and Dignity of this Nation; thus conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing ever to make the Sea our impregnable Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark, and our Fleets, what they ſo long have been, the Protection of our Friends, and the Terror of our Enemies. And to theſe Prayers, I'm ſure, not only You, but every true Engliſhman will ſay: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102495:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
